Einstein and the Bomb is a documentary, drama
film directed by Anthony Philipson.
What happened after Einstein fled Nazi Germany?
Using archival footage and his own words, this docudrama
dives into the mind of a tortured genius.
Albert Einstein, played by Aidan McArdle.
Commander Locker-Lampson, played by Andrew Havill.
Margery Howard, played by Rachel Barry.
Barbara Goodhall, played by Helena Westerman.
Katsu Hara, played by Leo Ashizawa.
Young Einstein, played by Jay Lewis Mitchell.
Albert Einstein (14 March 1879 – 18 April 1955) was a German-born theoretical
physicist best known for developing the theory of relativity.
Einstein also made important contributions to quantum theory.
His mass–energy equivalence formula E = mc2, which arises from special
relativity, has been called "the world's most famous equation".
He received the 1921 Nobel Prize in Physics for "his services to theoretical physics,
and especially for his discovery of the law of the photoelectric effect".
Born in the German Empire, Einstein moved to Switzerland in 1895, forsaking his German
citizenship (as a subject of the Kingdom of Württemberg) the following year.
In 1897, at the age of seventeen, he enrolled in the mathematics and physics teaching diploma
program at the Swiss federal polytechnic school in Zurich, graduating in 1900.
He acquired Swiss citizenship a year later, which he kept for the rest of his life, and
afterwards secured a permanent position at the Swiss Patent Office in Bern.
In 1905, he submitted a successful PhD dissertation to the University of Zurich.
In 1914, he moved to Berlin to join the Prussian Academy of Sciences and the Humboldt University of Berlin, becoming director of the Kaiser
Wilhelm Institute for Physics in 1917; he also became a German citizen again, this time as a subject of the Kingdom of Prussia.
In 1933, while Einstein was visiting the United States,
Adolf Hitler came to power in Germany.
Horrified by the Nazi persecution of his fellow Jews, he decided to remain
in the US, and was granted American citizenship in 1940.
On the eve of World War II, he endorsed a letter to President Franklin D.
Roosevelt alerting him to the potential German nuclear weapons program and recommending that
the US begin similar research, later carried out as the Manhattan Project.
In 1905, sometimes described as his annus mirabilis (miracle
year), he published four groundbreaking papers.
In them, he outlined a theory of the photoelectric effect, explained Brownian motion, introduced his special theory of
relativity, and demonstrated that if the special theory is correct, mass and energy are equivalent to each other.
In 1915, he proposed a general theory of relativity that extended
his system of mechanics to incorporate gravitation.
A paper that he published the following year laid out the implications of general relativity
for the modeling of the structure and evolution of the universe as a whole.
It introduced the cosmological constant and is further regarded as the
first step in the field of modern theoretical cosmology.
In 1917, Einstein wrote a paper which introduced the concepts of spontaneous emission and stimulated emission, the latter of which is the core mechanism behind the laser and
maser, and which contained a trove of information that would be beneficial to developments in physics later on, such as quantum electrodynamics and quantum optics.
In the middle part of his career, Einstein made important
contributions to statistical mechanics and quantum theory.
Especially notable was his work on the quantum physics of radiation, in
which light consists of particles, subsequently called photons.
With physicist Satyendra Nath Bose, he laid the
groundwork for Bose–Einstein statistics.
For much of the last phase of his academic life, Einstein worked on
two endeavors that ultimately proved unsuccessful.
First, he advocated against quantum theory's introduction of fundamental randomness into
science's picture of the world, objecting that "God does not play dice".
Second, he attempted to devise a unified field theory by generalizing his
geometric theory of gravitation to include electromagnetism.
As a result, he became increasingly isolated from mainstream modern physics.
Many  things are named after him, including the element Einsteinium.
In 1999, he was named Time's  Person of the Century.
The film explores themes of atomic bomb, atomic bomb test,
biography, based on true story, docudrama.
The tone is emotional.